Finding Aid for Cleland B. Wyllie papers, 1926-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Cleland B. Wyllie papers
1926-1979
Wyllie, Cleland B., 1906-1979.
85465 Aa 2
Director of media relations at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, articles, newsletters, annual reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, memorabilia, and miscellanea concerning trains and the railroad industry; also scrapbooks of Michigan sports.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Cleland B. Wyllie (donor no. 5327 ) and came to the library in 1979.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Born on October 30, 1906, in Durand, a railroad center, Cleland B. Wyllie worked for two years for the Grand Trunk and Western Railroad prior to enrolling at the University of Michigan in the fall of 1926.
After earning his bachelor's degree in 1930, he began his long career as journalist, first as telegraph editor for the Owosso Argus Press. He served in that post for five years before becoming editor of the Durand Express, a weekly newspaper. In 1937, Wyllie returned to the Owosso Argus Press as telegraph editor, and served in that post until becoming assistant editor of the U-M News Service in 1942.
Following a leave of absence from the U-M while serving in the U.S. Army from 1943 to 1945, Wyllie returned to Ann Arbor to assume his former duties. A year later he was promoted to editor of the U-M News Service. Wyllie's title was changed to managing editor in 1956 and, in 1962, he became assistant director of media relations for mass media. In 1965, his title was changed to that of U-M director of media relations.
Wyllie was a member of the Michigan Press Association, the Detroit Press Club, the University Club of Ann Arbor, and the Lexington Group, an organization of railroad historians. He served as publicity chairman for Michigan Week in 1970 and 1971.
Wyllie died early July, 1979.
The collection is arranged into five series: Correspondence; Writings; Railroads; Miscellaneous; and Scrapbooks. Much of the collection relates to Wyllie's great interest in railroad history.
Subjects:
Athletics--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Railroads--United States.; University of Michigan--Sports.Sports.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Blue Water Bridge (Port Huron, Mich. and Sarnia, Ont.); Ferries.; Mackinaw City (Mich.); Ontario.; Railroad lounge cars.; Railroads--Ontario.; Railroads--United States.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence, 1940-1979
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence with Herman H. Josenhans, 1958-1963 (Box 1)
- Writings, 1927
  - College papers and lecture notes, 1927-1929 (Box 1)
  - Articles, undated (Box 1)
  - Articles, for Inside Track, undated (Box 1)
  - "Black Hills Central Railroad,", undated (Box 1)
  - "Grand Trunk History, 1879-1880", undated (Box 1)
  - "Route of the Freight 4001s", undated (Box 1)
  - "Tyler vs. Vanderbilt,", undated (Box 1)
  - "Why have the railroads had to discontinue so many passenger trains in Michigan?", undated (Box 1)
  - "Can Michigan's Railroads Stay in the Passenger Business?", 1955 (Box 1)
  - "Railroad Passenger Service Needs Some Positive Thinking,", 1965 (Box 1)
  - "Train Riding Survey,", 1966-1968 (Box 1)
- Railroads
  - Papers concerning Michigan railroads, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Papers undated, 1972 concerning Michigan car ferries (Box 1)
  - Michigan Railroad Club
    - Membership list, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Broadsides, 1960-1974 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Rail Action Association undated, 1977 Constitution and bulletins (Box 1)
  - Railroad Record Club, undated, Order information (Box 1)
  - Roundhouse records Broadsides, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Railfan news release, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Papers, undated 1945, 1960-1961 concerning sale of timetables (Box 1)
  - Railroad memorabilia, undated, including broadsides, pamphlets, and certificates, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Articles by others concerning railroads and transportation, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1)
    (include obituary)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits (Box 1)
    - Railroad photos (Box 1)
  - Delta College (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - Of Michigan travel, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Concerning baseball, 1926 (Box 2)
  - Concerning football and baseball, 1926-1927 (Box 2)
  - Concerning sports, 1927-1928 (Box 2)
  - Concerning football and baseball, 1928-1930 (Box 2)
  - Concerning football, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - Of Michigan Rose Bowl game, 1948 (Box 2)